<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-08T10:15:45+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Creative Acts – Platform for Creative Activism</title><subtitle>Platform for Creative Activism</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Make the book</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/method/2014/12/01/make-the-book.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make the book" /><published>2014-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/method/2014/12/01/make-the-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/method/2014/12/01/make-the-book.html">&lt;p&gt;##How to print the book&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To print the book, download the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mastazine.net/handbook/download&quot;&gt;PDF file&lt;/a&gt; either of the whole book, or the chapter you want to print.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you use Adobe Acrobate, you will find the same options when printing as show in the pictures below.
First select print as “booklet”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choose “properties” and choose double sided print&amp;lt;
To bind the book, it is good to make sections, so called signatures. Therefore print pages in sections, first page 1-32, then 33 - 64 etc.
Fold the sections, and you are ready to bind the books!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##How to make the book
Here you find some binding techniques, of how to bind books.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jamiebutler.com/tutorials/bookbinding5.php&quot;&gt;http://www.jamiebutler.com/tutorials/bookbinding5.php&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://feelingbookish2010.blogspot.de/2010/11/piano-hinge-binding-by-leila-russon.html&quot;&gt;http://feelingbookish2010.blogspot.de/2010/11/piano-hinge-binding-by-leila-russon.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://merchesico.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/bookbinding-instructions-japanese-sewing-merge-leon.jpg&quot;&gt;http://merchesico.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/bookbinding-instructions-japanese-sewing-merge-leon.jpg&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/How-to-bind-your-own-Hardback-Book/?ALLSTEPS&quot;&gt;http://www.instructables.com/id/How-to-bind-your-own-Hardback-Book/?ALLSTEPS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">##How to print the book To print the book, download the PDF file either of the whole book, or the chapter you want to print. If you use Adobe Acrobate, you will find the same options when printing as show in the pictures below. First select print as “booklet”. Choose “properties” and choose double sided print&amp;lt; To bind the book, it is good to make sections, so called signatures. Therefore print pages in sections, first page 1-32, then 33 - 64 etc. Fold the sections, and you are ready to bind the books! ##How to make the book Here you find some binding techniques, of how to bind books. http://www.jamiebutler.com/tutorials/bookbinding5.php http://feelingbookish2010.blogspot.de/2010/11/piano-hinge-binding-by-leila-russon.html http://merchesico.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/bookbinding-instructions-japanese-sewing-merge-leon.jpg http://www.instructables.com/id/How-to-bind-your-own-Hardback-Book/?ALLSTEPS</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The first copies of Microevolutions in Berlin</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/10/07/the-first-copies-of-microevolutions-in-berlin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The first copies of Microevolutions in Berlin" /><published>2014-10-07T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-10-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/10/07/the-first-copies-of-microevolutions-in-berlin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/10/07/the-first-copies-of-microevolutions-in-berlin.html">&lt;p&gt;On the 20th of September, the first bookbinding event in Berlin took place, were visitors of the festival Recycled Creativity were invited to make their own copies of Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism. With great help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://kartonverlag.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Kartonverlag&lt;/a&gt; we discovered how to bind books, and we are getting prepared to do it again! For you who want to make your own copy of Microevolutions - be sure to save the date 1st of November!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was made possible with help of financial support from the Youth in Action programme, now known as the Erasmus+ program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/files/eu-logo.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 200px; height: 81px;&quot; /&gt;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On the 20th of September, the first bookbinding event in Berlin took place, were visitors of the festival Recycled Creativity were invited to make their own copies of Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism. With great help from Kartonverlag we discovered how to bind books, and we are getting prepared to do it again! For you who want to make your own copy of Microevolutions - be sure to save the date 1st of November! This project was made possible with help of financial support from the Youth in Action programme, now known as the Erasmus+ program. &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Issue #8: Unexpected</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/magazine/2014/09/29/issue-8-unexpected.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Issue #8: Unexpected" /><published>2014-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/magazine/2014/09/29/issue-8-unexpected</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/magazine/2014/09/29/issue-8-unexpected.html">&lt;p&gt;Mašta #8 UNEXPECTED is about breaking expectations. Inspired by the myth of growth, this Mašta goes further to open the field of expectations and explore the interactions between systems and people. Based on knowledge and only constrained by imagination, they might serve as a lighthouse or an audio-guide for the methaphorically deaf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tackle the obstacles built from fear of the unexpected  built not only by the same old evil corporations and conservative governments, but also by consumers and community members themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knock on the gates of the unexpected by visiting Spanish squares where people cry out for a united voice of society. We enter the struggle to reclaim public space in Kurdistan and basic human rights in The Fortress Europe. And when knocking on the gates is not enough we knock down the walls of expectations, following on the tracks of creative activism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Mašta #8 UNEXPECTED is about breaking expectations. Inspired by the myth of growth, this Mašta goes further to open the field of expectations and explore the interactions between systems and people. Based on knowledge and only constrained by imagination, they might serve as a lighthouse or an audio-guide for the methaphorically deaf. We tackle the obstacles built from fear of the unexpected  built not only by the same old evil corporations and conservative governments, but also by consumers and community members themselves. We knock on the gates of the unexpected by visiting Spanish squares where people cry out for a united voice of society. We enter the struggle to reclaim public space in Kurdistan and basic human rights in The Fortress Europe. And when knocking on the gates is not enough we knock down the walls of expectations, following on the tracks of creative activism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/09/18/microevolutions-a-practical-guide-to-creative-activism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism" /><published>2014-09-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/09/18/microevolutions-a-practical-guide-to-creative-activism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2014/09/18/microevolutions-a-practical-guide-to-creative-activism.html">&lt;p&gt;Its time for the microevolutions to see the daylight!
On saturday 20th of September, you can join us making the first books at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://recycledcreativity.info/de/&quot;&gt;Recycled Creativity festival&lt;/a&gt; in Berlin. The Masta crew will togheter with Kartonverlag provide the printed version of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mastazine.net/handbook/&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; and togheter we bind the very first copies in a experimental mood!
Come make your own copy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Its time for the microevolutions to see the daylight! On saturday 20th of September, you can join us making the first books at the Recycled Creativity festival in Berlin. The Masta crew will togheter with Kartonverlag provide the printed version of the book and togheter we bind the very first copies in a experimental mood! Come make your own copy!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/files/styles/medium/public/Mutation2.JPG" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Colophon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/2014/09/17/colophon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colophon" /><published>2014-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/2014/09/17/colophon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/2014/09/17/colophon.html">&lt;p&gt;Publication made by the Mašta collective. 
 Inspired by the activities and experiences of the network, the Mašta collective has created the “Microevolutions  - a practical guide to creative activism”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The handbook project started in 2013, this version of the book was created on &amp;lt;?php echo date('l, jS F Y')?&amp;gt;    *License *: &amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&amp;gt;CC-BY-SA 3.0&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;   &quot;Microevolutions  - a practical guide to creative activism&quot; is licensed under a  &amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&amp;gt;Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. This means that you are free to share, copy, distribute and transmit the work as well as to remix and adapt the work as long as you attribute the creator of the submission and Mašta. If you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute the resulting work only under the same or a similar license to this one.  We very much appreciate news about what you do with our work -  &amp;lt;a href=&quot;mailto:editor@mastazine.net&quot;&amp;gt;editor@mastazine.net&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;! 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Editorial team *
	Julia Vernersson, Ruta Vimba, Maria Perez, Laura Lara Sancez, Silvia Font, Maria Suarez Alvarez &lt;br /&gt;
  *Design, Web &amp;amp; PR *
	Cecilia Palmer, Malte Reißig, Jakob Dunning, Kito Colchester, Alise Ziemule, Katja Tegelj, Re.colectivo,  Anna-Lena Schroers, Sandra Wiesthal. 
  *Support   *
	Eilidh Lamb, Carla Fyfe, Maryne Nojac,  Janna Kunz, Vasilili, Luzumpunkts, Jose Maria Pérez Fernández, Gerben Grotenhuis, Martin Avila, Sheila J.F, Alicia Lopez Fariña, Tau, Clayton Mitchell, Elena Ballarin. 
  *Administration *
	Kulturlabor Trial&amp;amp;Error e. V., Ye Too Ponese, Xchange Scotland
&lt;img class=&quot;third&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/files/styles/small_without_crop/public/T%26E-logocolour_1.jpg?itok=gNZWLg_7&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;third&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/files/styles/small_without_crop/public/cabecera_YTP_0.jpg?itok=-5vwW6j0&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;third&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/assets/files/styles/small_without_crop/public/Untitled.png?itok=yLjrXILN&quot; /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trial-error-org/&quot;&gt;www.trial-error-org&lt;/a&gt;  //  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yetooponese.net/&quot;&gt;www.yetooponese.net&lt;/a&gt;  //  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xchangescotland.org/&quot;&gt;www.xchangescotland.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Publication made by the Mašta collective. Inspired by the activities and experiences of the network, the Mašta collective has created the “Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism”. The handbook project started in 2013, this version of the book was created on &amp;lt;?php echo date('l, jS F Y')?&amp;gt; *License *: &amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&amp;gt;CC-BY-SA 3.0&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; &quot;Microevolutions - a practical guide to creative activism&quot; is licensed under a &amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&amp;gt;Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. This means that you are free to share, copy, distribute and transmit the work as well as to remix and adapt the work as long as you attribute the creator of the submission and Mašta. If you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute the resulting work only under the same or a similar license to this one. We very much appreciate news about what you do with our work - &amp;lt;a href=&quot;mailto:editor@mastazine.net&quot;&amp;gt;editor@mastazine.net&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;! *Editorial team * Julia Vernersson, Ruta Vimba, Maria Perez, Laura Lara Sancez, Silvia Font, Maria Suarez Alvarez *Design, Web &amp;amp; PR * Cecilia Palmer, Malte Reißig, Jakob Dunning, Kito Colchester, Alise Ziemule, Katja Tegelj, Re.colectivo, Anna-Lena Schroers, Sandra Wiesthal. *Support * Eilidh Lamb, Carla Fyfe, Maryne Nojac, Janna Kunz, Vasilili, Luzumpunkts, Jose Maria Pérez Fernández, Gerben Grotenhuis, Martin Avila, Sheila J.F, Alicia Lopez Fariña, Tau, Clayton Mitchell, Elena Ballarin. *Administration * Kulturlabor Trial&amp;amp;Error e. V., Ye Too Ponese, Xchange Scotland www.trial-error-org // www.yetooponese.net // www.xchangescotland.org</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rhythms of Resistance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/any/10-20/2014/09/16/rhythms-of-resistance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rhythms of Resistance" /><published>2014-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/any/10-20/2014/09/16/rhythms-of-resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/any/10-20/2014/09/16/rhythms-of-resistance.html">&lt;p&gt;Existent groups of Rhythms of Resistance (RoR) are the network of action samba bands, playing for all kinds of socio-political and ecological causes. It exists to actively criticize and confront any form of domination, exploitation, discrimination or oppression and choose tactical frivolity and/or other forms of creative protest as a way to express rage and indignation of drumming participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replication of these ideas would be a requirement if you want to be a part of the network. Agree with them? In this case - creation of your band is possible under next principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;anti-hierarchical and egalitarian: striving to avoid all possible hierarchies (i.e., class, experiential, informational..) in our bands to develop sustainable structure where everyone feels equal and comfortable to express;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;anti-capitalist: striving not to replicate capitalist reproduction system within our bands due to critical view towards consumption, competition, unavoidable exploitation and other. Instead we try to create structures most acceptable for everyone which means we do not have any participation fee, all the band resources are communal, we try to develop solidarity support and egalitarian methods of compensation if needed. That is also the reason why, for example, we try to create d.i.y. instruments or reuse old ones;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;anti-sexist and anti-racist: striving for maximum accessibility for all genders and races (also ages and classes) in bands where different people feel comfortable and equally valued. This principle implies reflections about dynamics in the group and creation of safe space for everyone to be able to speak out their issues related as well as learning more on issues of structural domination by your own or collectively;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;fighting for social and ecological justice: striving to support fights against social oppressions or ecological destruction or initiating them. This is the external goal of samba activists using samba as a form of political action.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;tactical frivolity: using methods inspired by carnival to confront and criticize any system of domination. That means we engage humor and dressing up as a technic to distract. At the same time we reject any false opposition between militancy and creative forms of resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;open: striving to spread information about network existing and being open for joining to any people who share our principle.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested to join? Research on local bands in your town and try it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there are no such present yet, check out what can help you to start your group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing a Kick-off meeting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gather information you consider important for people to know about RoR. Compress essential part in one input and create means which can help you in spreading the info: flyers, posters, stickers, posts in social networks and so on. Do not forget to mention time and spot for meeting and how long discussion could last! Be aware of spreading info in different places attended by different kinds of people if you intend to attract diverse crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the meeting actually starts, it is important to think about agenda, prepare exercises to introduce people to each other, prepare a space and about other facilitation (moderation) issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kick-off meeting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure theoretical information is clear, discuss important issues: how you would like to make decisions, do you all understand and agree with principles, what can be your meeting place and time, which instruments you want to use, how do you think you can learn tunes. Collect contacts of the people and agree on communication means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meeting can last for hours due to amount of important issues to discuss. It is good also to postpone parts of important discussion for further on and give other people chance to facilitate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping the Flow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is something ideally everyone in the band is responsible for. If you decide that the Principles are actual for you, it is not enough to only state it. Due to imperfections of our world and deep influence of the society, it is in most cases not so easy to be anti-sexist, -racist, -classist egalitarian person, even if we want so. Therefore constant reflections are needed and enough care to keep safe space for people to be able to speak up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Existent groups of Rhythms of Resistance (RoR) are the network of action samba bands, playing for all kinds of socio-political and ecological causes. It exists to actively criticize and confront any form of domination, exploitation, discrimination or oppression and choose tactical frivolity and/or other forms of creative protest as a way to express rage and indignation of drumming participants.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Singing Skopjans</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/interviews/interview/2014/09/16/singing-skopjans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Singing Skopjans" /><published>2014-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/interviews/interview/2014/09/16/singing-skopjans</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/interviews/interview/2014/09/16/singing-skopjans.html">&lt;p&gt;A song won’t bring a repressive government down but it can piss it off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singing Skopjans (Распеани скопјани) is an activist choir based in Skopje, Macedonia. Their actions in the public space represent “an attempt to intervene in the violent polarized discourse in which the voices of the different are not heard, but the voices of the more powerful are”. They describe themselves as a thought articulated in music and performance that tackles the current social and political issues in the city and the world in which they live in. As they say for themselves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Singing Skopjans performs as one, but they are not one in any case. Singing Skopjans is a performance, a play and political reasoning.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: What were the reasons for you to organize a socially and politically conscious self-organized choir which resist the current government polices, critiques the social circumstances and gives support to other activist initiatives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years, we were attempting to turn ourselves in the public discourse and in re-thinking of society in which we live and what we want it to be. We are frequently trying out different forms of inclusion, but generally we are dealing with the rule of the more powerful and forceful. Maybe this form of communication causes less attention on the point we are trying to make. When resistance is concerned, it is in the root of the reasons why we exist after we were violently chased away from the main square in Skopje on March 28th, 2009 (http://globalvoicesonline.org/2009/03/31/macedonia-student-protest-ends-… ), we have decided the we will constantly return to that square with a song and we will be sending a message that the square is ours after all, and it won’t be a public square if it wasn’t so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: What is the way in which the choir is organized? Is it completely horizontally organized or is there some kind of a hierarchy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no hierarchy – each current member equally contributes in the decisions of the current actions of the choir. No matter if the decision is about the choice of an occasion, a song, a location of filming or other creative idea about choreography, use of items or something similar, everything is discussed in the group (on our mailing list or our “classes” which we organize from time to time) and is performed in a democratic manner: We adopt the suggestion which the majority will pass and then we start to prepare the action. The only thing in which we do not get involved is the musical part, we do not interfere in expertize of our conductor and we accept his/her professional suggestion without judgmental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: Are you completely open so far membership in the choir is concerned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone who wants to be a member of the choir has sung a song with us. People come to us on their own – some of them are our friends and acquaintances, some of them are completely unknown persons who find us on the social networks. None of our members were “scanned” or checked; we function on the principle of trust and we consider that everyone who approaches the choir should at least agree with a part of our potions or if they have their own- to share them with us. However, it has happened that members of the choir leave due to different reasons and that is how the filtering and fluctuation actually occurs: some simply do not have the time and energy to dedicate themselves to the rehearsals, discussions and endless brainstorming. On the other hand, some do not see themselves in the messages that the choir conveys, others are simply afraid. However, the choir has always been open for everyone who has sung  and for those who like to sing. Luckily, there are at least always 15 people who are in the mood to take a part of their time and energy to create some new arrangement, new cover or commentary of the issues that concern us in the country and in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: Which is the criteria by which you choose the songs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to have an effect of our performances, the song has to suit the occasion. Sometimes that connection is made immediately, but in some situations we listen to dozens of suggestions, we discuss them in our mailing list until we vote and agree on the most suitable suggestion. It is important to us that the lyrics of the song are in the context of what we are singing about (we do not want to change the original lyrics of the songs a lot, even though we sometimes do make minimal changes of a word or a verse). It is also important that the chosen song is familiar, because the popular songs reach people more easily and so they turn the attention on the issues. We are satisfied the most, when besides being familiar, catchy and suitable for being covered, the song also represents a musical piece that we like to listen to (which is not always the case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: The verbal violence that frequently occurs in the social environment is in many occasions transformed into physical violence. How much do you think that this type of non-violent protest can be efficient in bringing social and political changes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first catch-phrase that the Macedonian audience connected to the Singing Skopjans when they first appeared is “who is singing, thinks no evil” (a famous Macedonian saying – interviewers note). We, on the other hand, have a different motto “who sings, thinks”. The one who decides to sing, instead of cheering and using stones and fists, has understood that the stones and the fists only bring more stones and fists. The violent changes are ineffective, are covered in blood and are short-term. We are an activist choir, not an artist group. However, we have chosen music as a mode of expressing revolt and we expect that the way in which we will influence the changes will be like that: every art form influences indirectly, on a subtle level. Music makes evolutions more often than revolutions, and we need an evolution. We hope that other cities will start to sing as well, that the fear will disappear. And when we are not afraid, we can achieve a lot. Every time we get discouraged we ask ourselves if there is any effect of our struggle, but we remember how the politicians of the ruling party call us by our names in the media, they “research” our family trees and bank accounts, using all of the available means to discredit us individually in order to disarm us collectively. All of that, because of signing a song. Is there a bigger evidence than that on the issue that what we do still creates an effect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: Which are the ways in which you promote and share the actions with the general population?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our street performances are unannounced, so in the moment of action we are singing to the people which are currently on the location. Sometimes it occurs to attract their attention, other times we are just ignored. However, every action is filmed and uploaded on our YouTube channel. For there on, every video lives its own life: we, the members of the choir and everyone who thinks that our message is relevant in the given moment, can share it on Facebook. The best insight of the relevance are the numbers of views of our videos. Some are viewed more them thousand times. However, we must not forget the shares of our “haters” who, even though spiced up with a hateful comment and an insult, still contribute to the spreading of our messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mašta: Despite the frequent verbal attacks in the comments on the social networks, has it ever occurred to you to be attacked physically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something like that has not occurred yet, eventhough there were pretty “graphic” threads toward us. However, that is not always excluded. When we only remind ourselves of the brutal attacks that happened in Skopje between groups and individuals from different nationalities or sexual orientation, or when we remind ourselves of the brutal demolitions of the LGBT support (http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a7FlhIOmhFg) center in the Old Bazaar in Skopje, there is a reason to think that we just weren’t put in the same place and time with our aggressive opponents and that there wasn’t a song and occasion that would have provoked physical violence.
Mašta: You have also performed with different activist choirs from the region. How much does the focus in the choice of the direction of action of the other activist choirs differs from your own ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had the luck and the great pleasure in several occasions to perform, hang out and exchange experiences with other activist choirs in the region such as Kombinat, Le Zbor, Horkestar, Svetonazori, Prrroba and others. We noticed that each one of these choirs has a general focus: social rights, women rights and rights of the LGBT community, critique of the rising nationalism, etc. We also deal with these issues, as well as with our local, urban topics and problems. However, this leaves the impression that all of the states from former Yugoslavia are troubled with the same problems such as social inequality, violation of basic human rights, especially woman’s rights, homophobia, nationalism, clericalism, fascism and other local madness which are usually helped by the ruling elites. On our common meetings and performances we remind ourselves and we additionally motivate each other to keep singing and to try to make a difference, each in his own country. It is always nice to know that you are not alone in the struggle for justice, equality and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A song won’t bring a repressive government down but it can piss it off. Singing Skopjans (Распеани скопјани) is an activist choir based in Skopje, Macedonia. Their actions in the public space represent “an attempt to intervene in the violent polarized discourse in which the voices of the different are not heard, but the voices of the more powerful are”. They describe themselves as a thought articulated in music and performance that tackles the current social and political issues in the city and the world in which they live in. As they say for themselves:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The neurons - Inspiration from outside</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/perspectives/perspective/2014/09/09/the-neurons-inspiration-from-outside.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The neurons - Inspiration from outside" /><published>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/perspectives/perspective/2014/09/09/the-neurons-inspiration-from-outside</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/perspectives/perspective/2014/09/09/the-neurons-inspiration-from-outside.html">&lt;p&gt;Cells communicate with others and take information from outside. Our neurons got some input from these inspirators: &lt;em&gt;Paulo Freire and Pedagogy of the oppressed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Education could be a subversive force&quot;, - Paulo Freire&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paulo Freire is a Brasilian educator and philosopher who is a leading advocate of critical pedagogy. He is well know for his influential work, ‘Pedagogy of the Oppressed’ which is considered one of the fundational texts of the critical pedagogy movement. While working, Freire became aware of the economic, political, and social domination resulting from paternalism. Paternalism leads to a culture of silence, which keeps people from confronting their oppression. He turned this philosophy to pedagogy because “the whole education system was one of the major instruments for the maintenance of this culture of silence.” One of Freire’s central tenets was that “education is freedom” that leads toward true liberation and that the “banking” concept of education - where students are empty vessels to be filled, acts as an instrument of oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His philosophy on education centers on critical consciousness, where the oppressed recognize the causes of their oppression “so that through transformative action they can create a new situation, which makes possible the pursuit of fuller humanity.” He introduced problem-posing education; this type of education, in opposition to banking education, involves “listening, dialogue and action” and is an instrument that leads people to grow their consciousness and to social transformation.
His work, theory and concepts have influenced lots of people to action and social transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freire.org/&quot; title=&quot;http://www.freire.org/&quot;&gt;http://www.freire.org/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pedagogyoftheoppressed.com/&quot; title=&quot;http://www.pedagogyoftheoppressed.com/&quot;&gt;http://www.pedagogyoftheoppressed.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Saul Alinsky’s community organizing model###&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“My critics are right when they call me an outside agitator. When a community, any kind of community, is hopeless and helpless, it requires somebody from outside to come in and stir things up. That's my job -- to unsettle them, to make them start asking questions, to teach them to stop talking and start acting, because the fat cats in charge never hear with their ears, only through their rears&quot;, - Saul Alinsky.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saul Alinsky began community organising career in the late 1930s. As a part of his field research job as a graduate student in criminology at the University of Chicago he was to develop a juvenile delinquency program in Chicago’s “Back of the Yards,” neighborhood downwind of the Chicago Stockyards–a foul-smelling and crime-ridden slum. When Alinsky arrived, the Congress of Industrial Organizations was organising the stockyard workers living there. Expanding the CIO model beyond workplace issues, Alinsky organized the Back of the Yards Neighborhood Council (BYNC) from local neighborhood groups, ethnic clubs, union locals, bowling leagues and an American Legion Post. The success of BYNC in getting expanded city services and political power started Alinsky off on a long career of organizing poor urban communities around the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His theory said that behind every successful social movement there is a community or a network of communities.These communities don’t just happen. They must be organized. Someone has to build strong enough relationships between people so they can support each other through long and sometimes dangerous social change struggles. Or, if the community already exists, someone has to help transform it to support political action. Sometimes that requires reorganizing the community by identifying individuals who can move the community to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process of building a mobilisable community is called “community organizing.” It involves “the craft” of building an enduring network of people, who identify with common ideals and who can engage in social action on the basis of those ideals. Community organizing is the process of building power that includes people with a problem in defining their community, defining the problems that they wish to address, the solutions they wish to pursue and the methods they will use to accomplish their solutions. In general, community organizing is the work that occurs in local settings to empower individuals, build relationships and create action for social change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Cells communicate with others and take information from outside. Our neurons got some input from these inspirators: Paulo Freire and Pedagogy of the oppressed</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 5 Ws and How</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/the-5-ws-and-how.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 Ws and How" /><published>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/the-5-ws-and-how</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/the-5-ws-and-how.html">&lt;p&gt;Before the exercise prepare six signs: Why, What, Who, Where, When and How.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divide into 6 groups. Give each person a paper with Why, What, Who, Where, When and How. Ask them to move around and organize themselves in a way so that they show the order of importance or the chronological order you need to answer to each question when you are organizing an action. This will create a discussion: “What comes first, because you need to know what you want to do?”, “Why comes first, because you need a reason to do what you do?”. Leave some time to discuss and reach an agreement. When they agree, try to challenge their decision with questions that make them reflect about their preconceptions like: “If your action is about changing a neighborhood, then the first one will be “Where”, right?” “Do you always have a reason before you start to do something and does your reason  change while doing it?”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Before the exercise prepare six signs: Why, What, Who, Where, When and How.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simulation game - game of boxes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/simulation-game-game-of-boxes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simulation game - game of boxes" /><published>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-09-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/simulation-game-game-of-boxes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/handbook/methods/method/1%20hour/any/3-10/2014/09/09/simulation-game-game-of-boxes.html">&lt;p&gt;Firstly participants individually reflect about three concrete issues that concern or affect them. After 10 min individuals gather in small groups of four or five people. If the group is small, it could be as well in groups of three. The groups share the topics and choose one for the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that we present 3 boxes: in one of them there are folded papers with names of places, for example, university, shopping centre, school, village, etc…; in another one there are folded papers with different target groups: women, kids, consumers, etc….; in the other one there are folded papers with creative activism techniques with an explanation: craftivism, performance, light graffiti, theatre, etc… Each group can choose one paper from each box so they have a topic + a place + a target group and technique to design an action together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the groups are ready with their actions you can either provide time for them to go “ hands on “ and try out the action or directly analyze them in plenary without trying them. In both cases, keep time for groups to present and analyze their action taking in account the different factors (topic, place, target group and technique) and their relations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Firstly participants individually reflect about three concrete issues that concern or affect them. After 10 min individuals gather in small groups of four or five people. If the group is small, it could be as well in groups of three. The groups share the topics and choose one for the group.</summary></entry></feed>